<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero in English]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero's blog]]></description>
        <link>https://juancman.dev/en</link>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 02:10:42 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://juancman.dev/en-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rewind 2023 and future plans]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>Rewind 2023 and future plans</h1>
<p><img src="/blog/rewind-2023-and-future-plans/banner.jpg" alt="A sunset with a sign"><br><em>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@soymeraki?utm_content=creditCopyText&utm_medium=referral&utm_source=unsplash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Javier Allegue Barros</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/silhouette-of-road-signage-during-golden-hour-C7B-ExXpOIE?utm_content=creditCopyText&utm_medium=referral&utm_source=unsplash" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Unsplash</a></em></p>
<PostData date='December 16, 2023' author='Juan Manzanero' />

<p>I hope you are having a good time this holiday.</p>
<p>Life is a succession of choices, and in retrospect, I&#39;m happy that this year I made the right ones.</p>
<h2>In retrospect about my career this 2023</h2>
<p>I grew up drastically as a Full Stack Developer, learning new libraries and establishing my tech stack.</p>
<p>I even started hacking (not the thing you hear in the news), creating side projects looking to create solutions.</p>
<p>I updated this website, creating new functionalities for content creation.</p>
<p>Now I have more confidence in my skills, ready to keep growing up and taking on new challenges.</p>
<h2>Futures plans for my career this 2024</h2>
<p>I want to start freelancing, I&#39;ll be creating templates and demo projects for selling my services as a Frontend Developer mainly, but I&#39;ll keep learning about backend and cloud, as well as keep practicing my English to enter the USA or European markets.</p>
<p>Maybe I&#39;ll not achieve this in 2024, but I must keep growing, as each year passes, I&#39;ll be more prepared.</p>
<p>I&#39;ll check if I could contribute to an Open Source project, as almost every tool that I use is an Open Source one, I couldn&#39;t be here without if not with the help of Open Source projects.</p>
<p>Honestly, my true wish is to work full time in a Software as a Service startup, or any startup with a focus on Software.</p>
<p>The good thing that is I keep growing professionally, and I expect (and will) the next year I&#39;ll reach more milestones.</p>
<p>And of course, I&#39;ll continue hacking (in a creative way, not stealing info or criminal things) with side projects, creating an extra incoming source will be great for my finances.</p>
<h2>Retrospect of 2023 personally and more</h2>
<p>This year I rediscovered the hobby of reading, and I really enjoy it.</p>
<p>I discovered my new favorite book, <strong>Ready Player One</strong>, it was a really exciting and great lecture, the next year I&#39;ll read the sequel.</p>
<p>I also started reading <strong>Ikigai</strong>, to keep acquiring good habits for a long and happy life, and seek a purpose in life.</p>
<p>Another book I started reading is <strong>The Little Book of Common Sense Investing</strong>, as I already had a good habit of saving, but I want my money to keep growing more for a dignified retirement.</p>
<p>I&#39;m spending less time on social media, <a href="https://www.juancman.dev/en/blog/the-monotony-of-social-media" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">even I wrote an article about this</a>, doing things that <strong>I really want to do</strong> instead.</p>
<p>Is really horrible how much time social media steals from us, keeping us away from doing things that we really enjoy.</p>
<p>I&#39;m doing moderate exercise, but indoors, I want to go outdoors too, I need more solar light.</p>
<p>I&#39;m happy spending my time with my family, even if the majority of the time I&#39;m working or studying, I keep contact with my loved ones, and continue doing it, clearly.</p>
<h2>Future plans for 2024 personally and more</h2>
<p>I&#39;ll keep reading, I&#39;ll write more on this website.</p>
<p>I want to acquire new habits, like pixel art.</p>
<p>And I&#39;m retaking an old hobby, <strong>GameDev</strong>.</p>
<p>As Unity is doing questionable things, I&#39;ll be using <a href="https://godotengine.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Godot</a> instead.</p>
<p>I don&#39;t have in mind a big project or something like that, just retake to develop simple videogames demos, it would be great to launch a little videogame, but a complete one.</p>
<p>Trust me, is really, <strong>REALLY</strong> challenging to develop videogames, so instead of overwhelming myself, I&#39;ll keep my <strong>ambitions simple</strong>, but <strong>constant</strong>.</p>
<h3>Happy holidays!</h3>
<p><img src="/blog/rewind-2023-and-future-plans/2023-complete!.png" alt="2023 complete image!"></p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://juancman.dev/en/blog/rewind-2023-and-future-plans</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://juancman.dev/en/blog/rewind-2023-and-future-plans</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Thoughts]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2023 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Peddler App]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>Peddler App</h1>
<p><img src="/blog/peddler-app/peddler-app-banner.png" alt="Peddler App provisional logo"><br><em>Peddler App provisional logo</em></p>
<PostData date='November 12, 2023' author='Juan Manzanero' />

<h2>The idea</h2>
<p>You hear the ice cream man in his truck, you try to catch him, but the guy is already far away.</p>
<p>Why not get a notification on your phone when the ice cream man is near you? So you can just tap the notification and request the ice cream man to go to your location.</p>
<p>That&#39;s the purpose of this app.</p>
<h2>Overwhelming for me</h2>
<p>I&#39;d never developed a big app just by myself, but I want to try and see what happens.</p>
<p>I want to follow the Indie Hacker way, sharing in public the progress, and getting feedback from the community.</p>
<p>This post is the first step before designing in Figma or even creating the landing page, so I want to hear if you&#39;re interested, why you&#39;re not, or what would be great for the app.</p>
<h2>Starting small</h2>
<p>I really want to start small, launching a Minimum Viable Product (MVP), with the next features:</p>
<ul>
<li>User registration and login</li>
<li>Two types of users, peddlers and customers</li>
<li>Peddlers<ul>
<li>If the user is a peddler (wants to sell), redirect to the peddler form</li>
<li>Peddlers can create a profile with the name of their company and products that offer, for example ice cream, candy, etc</li>
<li>Once the registration is finished, peddlers can start routes</li>
<li>The app gets the location of the peddler, showing it on a map</li>
<li>The backend will detect if the peddler enters a radius of a customer, and send a push notification to the customer</li>
<li>Once the peddler has a request, the app will show the location of the requesting customer on the map</li>
<li>The peddler can go to the destination, and fulfill the transaction</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Customers<ul>
<li>Customers can just create a profile with their name or alias, and set locations, for example: house</li>
<li>Once a peddler is near, the backend will send a notification to the customer</li>
<li>If the customer taps and confirms the notification</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, customers would change notifications settings and more, but that&#39;s the core idea.</p>
<p>For the MVP I don&#39;t want to implement in-app payments, but of course, it could be a future feature.</p>
<h2>What do you think?</h2>
<p>Please tell me what you think, you can email me at <a href="mailto:contact@juancman.dev" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">contact@juancman.dev</a></p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://juancman.dev/en/blog/peddler-app</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://juancman.dev/en/blog/peddler-app</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Tech]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[SideProject]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I participated in a Hackathon]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>I participated in a Hackathon</h1>
<p><img src="/blog/i-participated-in-a-hackathon/i-participated-in-a-hackathon-banner.png" alt="Tech Stack"><br><em>Tech stack used: Supabase, Next.js and Shadcn/UI, My first hackathon!</em></p>
<PostData date='August 16, 2023' author='Juan Manzanero' />

<p>I recently participated in a <a href="https://supabase.com/blog/supabase-lw8-hackathon" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Supabase Hackathon</a>, forming a team with people from other countries, one from Bangladesh and the other person from Brazil, obviously using English for communication on Discord.</p>
<p>The Hackathon thematic was free, the only main rule is to use Supabase for any feature, like authentication, as a PostgreSQL database or using vectors for AI, with 10 days to build a product using any technology and upload it in a GitHub repository.</p>
<p>We developed an e-commerce app with a Walmart products model, implementing vectors for better search results.</p>
<p>Using Supabase we implemented auth and protected routes so the user needs to log in to see recommendations and more.</p>
<p>The user can add products to the shopping cart and check their items for saved it and see recommendations and which items are frequently bought.</p>
<p>My main role was focused on creating the UI using the Next.js 13 app router, protecting routes only for authenticated users, and create reusable components such as product cards, and of course, making the layout responsive for mobile and desktop.</p>
<p>We used <a href="https://ui.shadcn.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Shadcn/UI</a> as those components are already implemented functionalities with accessibility like modals or sidebars, like the sidebar that appears when you’re on a mobile device and open the button in the header, with a smooth animation.</p>
<p>We submitted the project on time and waiting for the results, and this is my first time participating in a Hackathon, I really enjoy it and hope to continue contributing to the project on GitHub.</p>
<p>It&#39;s amazing work with people from other countries, using English even if is not our native language, but with a purpose in common, create a great product.</p>
<p>I’ll keep looking to participate in more Hackathons in the future and contribute to open source projects on Github because I really enjoy the feeling of developing something big with more people.</p>
<p>I learned too much in these few days, like integrating Next.js with Supabase for authentication and protected routes, using the Supabase docs as a guide, and using it for the first time Shadcn/UI, and looking forward to keep using it.</p>
<p>It took me so long to participate in a Hackathon, as before I hesitated about my experience, but the reality is we’ll never be ready for new challenges because if you’re already ready it means that’s too late.</p>
<p>I want to learn more about using vectors for AI, so I’ll investigate more about the topic, as the tech tends to go that way, who knows what would be the next big tech trend or when.</p>
<p><a href="https://groce-wise.vercel.app/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">You can see the project: Grocewise here</a></p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://juancman.dev/en/blog/i-participated-in-a-hackathon</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://juancman.dev/en/blog/i-participated-in-a-hackathon</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Tech]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Hobby]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Hackathon]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Monotony of Social Media]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>The Monotony of Social Media</h1>
<p><img src="/blog/the-monotony-of-social-media/the-monotony-of-social-media-banner.jpg" alt="Person checking social media"><br><em>Person checking social media. Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@fantasyflip?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Austin Distel</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/iIJrUoeRoCQ?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Unsplash</a></em></p>
<PostData date='July 17, 2023' author='Juan Manzanero' />

<p>It’s obvious, a lot of interactions on the Internet occurs through social media, letting you send friend requests, chat, or share memes and photos. However, abstracting human interaction using software has caused many problems that didn’t exist before.</p>
<p>When the Internet started, many people created their own websites because that&#39;s was the thing you must have if you want to be cool, and a lot of these websites was just blogpost-like where the users shares their hobbies like movies, sports, books, videogames, etc. This motivation made more unique and human websites, where you can meet someone and their likes or dislikes.</p>
<p>Now, with the boom of social media in the middle of 2000&#39;s, people prefer to connect just searching for a name or looking the friends of their friends, and send friend requests to try and connect. That was cool at the start, as anything new, but the problems started when companies like Facebook (now Meta) or Google (with YouTube) needed to monetize their platforms, mostly with Ads.</p>
<p>And of course, that means that they needed to suppress, censor or ban anything that could be harmful for society, like hate speeches or stupid challenges that could risk people&#39;s lives.</p>
<p>But, the bat thing about this, is that they homogenize almost everyone, forcing them to act as the algorithms keeps recommending users with likes and comments, guiding the people to act like someone else, and so.</p>
<p>Now almost everyone does mainly two things, post photos about their &quot;perfect&quot; lives or share memes, and don&#39;t get me wrong, it&#39;s ok to enter to social media and try to disconnect for your job or problems, but using this every day as instant escape instead of confronting your own problems could be harmful in the long term, isolating you from the need of socialize in real life, with real people, and thinking that everyone has a perfect life.</p>
<p>No, EVERYONE has problems in their lives, even more than yours, but social media algorithms promotes mainly &quot;positive vibes only&quot; and all that shit that in big dose is hamrful for our minds.</p>
<p>And don&#39;t mention the censorship and shadow-banning if you post something controversial, it could be something that should not be tolerated like incite hate to a group, or it could be something that don&#39;t everyone agrees but it could be useful think a little about it, but still being controversial.</p>
<p>Should everyone can tell what they thinks? Yeah, always if doesn&#39;t promotes hate or hurt other people or animals.</p>
<p>They&#39;re reports like Twitter promotes hate in the algorithm, and Meta knows that Instagram increases anxiety and depression on young people, and actually; promotes it... as all negative feelings keeps you on the social media interacting with others, as that&#39;s what those companies sell, your data and time to advertisers.</p>
<p>I recently heard a video talking about this topic, and that would be cool if we go back as the starts of the Internet where people created content as a hobby, instead of looking for validation through likes and comments, being more authentic persons instead of products.</p>
<p>Should software solutions replace human interactions? I think not, but it&#39;s too late for almost everyone, but if you&#39;re reading this, start changing your life first if you want to be honest with yourself.</p>
<hr>
<p>Blog inspired by &quot;Why does every personal website look like this now?&quot; by Eric Murphy on YouTube.</p>
<p>Source Video:</p>
<iframe
  width='560'
  height='315'
  src='https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/_x6SCSz7g5I'
  title='YouTube video player'
  frameBorder='0'
  allow='accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share'
  allowFullScreen
/>
]]></description>
            <link>https://juancman.dev/en/blog/the-monotony-of-social-media</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://juancman.dev/en/blog/the-monotony-of-social-media</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Thoughts]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Computers Works]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>How Computers Works</h1>
<p><img src="/blog/how-computers-works/philipp-katzenberger-iIJrUoeRoCQ-unsplash.jpg" alt="Open laptop"><br><em>An open laptop. Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@fantasyflip?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText'" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Philipp Katzenberger</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/iIJrUoeRoCQ?utm_source=unsplash&utm_medium=referral&utm_content=creditCopyText" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Unsplash</a></em></p>
<PostData date='May 29, 2023' author='Juan Manzanero' />

<p>Today we use, in some way, the computer in almost every activity in our lives, it could be for work or just fun, but if we think carefully, computers are an invention from the previous century, and have changed our lives.</p>
<p>New works have appeared, new careers to study, and new problems to be solved.</p>
<p>However, do we know how computers penetrated our lives? Do we know how a computer works? How does the Internet work?</p>
<p>Many people use their smartphones to communicate with family and friends and to share their lives, but they don’t know how all this is possible.</p>
<p>I’m not saying that everyone needs to be a Software Engineer or IT Expert, but knowing about this could be outstanding knowledge.</p>
<hr>
<h2>The power of computers</h2>
<hr>
<p>Computers can expand our brains, such things like sends messages to people from the other side of the Earth, to create an app that speeds up delivery.</p>
<p>All these things are possible by flipping 0’s and 1’s, but how is this possible?</p>
<p>If you&#39;ve watched The Imitation Code, maybe you know this story.</p>
<h3>Computing Fundaments</h3>
<hr>
<p>Alan Turing was the inventor of the Turing Machine, a simple but powerful machine that can receive instructions to move along a long tape, changing the state of each slot. This three things, a head, a long tape and a set of instructions are the bases for the modern computers.</p>
<p>The head is the Central Processing Unit (CPU), a piece of hardware that can be used for general purposes, receiving instructions (Algorithm) whose are transformed to electric pulses, understanding if electricity pass trough or not, if it&#39;s true or false, 1 or 0. All these instructions are saved in a Random Access Memory (RAM) for a quick access of the work that needs to be accomplished, and using a Read-Only Memory (ROM) to store persistent data that needs to be saved even if the computer shuts down.</p>
<p>An algorithm&#39;s like a recipe, declaring ingredients (variables) and the steps to follow to achieve the result (functions).</p>
<p>A variable is an identifier that points to a slot of memory in the RAM, storing a value that can be a number, a text (known as “string”), a boolean (true or false), or an object (a set of multiple variables and functions that can be instanced), etc.</p>
<p>Functions are blocks of instructions that achieve a task, like obtaining your current location or sending a message.</p>
<p>And maybe you are asking, how do I tell a computer how to do what I want?</p>
<h3>Programming languages</h3>
<hr>
<p>If you try to speak with someone who doesn’t speak the same language as you, you try to use a translator or use gestures, something that you know that both can in some way understand, the same is for computers.</p>
<p>Computers are powerful, but they need someone to tell them what to do, this is work for humans, and to achieve it we use programming languages. With a programming language you use a specific syntax to tell a computer your desired task, then you compile that file where you type all your instructions, when a file compiles, is transformed to a computer nature language (1’s and 0’s) and then the computer executes the task.</p>
<p>There are different programming languages, and all of them are designed to achieve specific needs, like the programming languages C and C++, both are low-level languages, which means that are close to how a computer “speaks” and are used to control and administrate memory in high-efficient apps, or to illuminate the screen of your computer.</p>
<p>There is Java, is a language that can create an environment when is compiled, meaning that can be used on almost every computer.</p>
<p>JavaScript (is NOT Java or something like that) is a language that our browsers understands, with the help of JavaScript, we can access to a web page and see nice interactions when we click a button, login with a username and password, and more.</p>
<p>JavaScript is a high-level language, that is easiest to learn than Java or C, but not that is worse or better, just resolves a different need.</p>
<h3>The Browser</h3>
<hr>
<p>A powerful software that can access other computers using the Hyper Text Transfer Protocol (HTTP), it means that thanks to this protocol different computers can send and receive information to communicate, even if they’re far away. The browsers receive data in the form of a file, mainly three:</p>
<ul>
<li>Hyper Text Markup Language (HTML)</li>
<li>Cascading Styles Sheet (CSS)</li>
<li>JavaScript</li>
</ul>
<h3>HTML</h3>
<p>Helps the browser to structure data like texts or images, using a markup language (tags). The browser can know where to put an input to type your email or a button to subscribe to your favorite artist.</p>
<h3>CSS</h3>
<p>It gives colors and forms to the HTML tags using selectors. It can be used to change page&#39;s background color, change button&#39;s rounded borders, modify text color, and everything your creativity can give.</p>
<h3>JavaScript</h3>
<p>Combining HTML and CSS with JavaScript creates an interactive web site, or web app (like this one). You can for example, add a button that changes the theme to dark/light, or store items in a shopping cart and show a number of items you have.</p>
<p>For all this you need to store your files somewhere, letting people access a computer to download all these files using their browsers, that&#39;s the functionality of servers.</p>
<p>Servers are computers that are connected to the Internet, and store files that can be downloaded or uploaded using protocols and security rules. Some companies like Google or Microsoft have multiple centers with many servers in different regions of the planet, called Data Centers, and can be used with a fee for storing your web app, these multiple Data Centers are called Cloud.</p>
<h3>The Cloud</h3>
<p>Administrating a powerful computer can be difficult, but if you know how to use it, you can save a lot of money instead of maintaining local computers that need to be turned on 24/7. Thanks to the cloud we can deliver the fastest apps, and we can have a 24/7 service for our customers with a marginal cost.</p>
<h2>Computers Changed Humanity</h2>
<hr>
<p>Computers simplifies our daily tasks, software can be easy replicated and distributed without need of logistics like a tangible product. You just need an Internet connection to reach someone’s project.</p>
<p>You don’t need a factory or natural resources like wood to produce paper, you need a group of engineers, UX/UI designers, digital marketers, and more IT people to reach billions of customers.</p>
<p>The reason that computers are too powerful is that the marginal cost is minimal, you don’t need to extract something from the earth to build an app, you need a group of talented persons that uses their brains to create solutions.</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://juancman.dev/en/blog/how-computers-works</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://juancman.dev/en/blog/how-computers-works</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Tech]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Informatic]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The reason to create a version 2.0 of my website]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>The reason to create a version 2.0 of my website</h1>
<p><img src="/blog/website-2.0/website-2.0-header.png" alt="Tech stack"><br><em>Tech Stack of this website. Next.js, Vercel, React.js, TypeScript and TailwindCSS</em></p>
<PostData date='April 7, 2023' author='Juan Manzanero' />

<p>The first version of my website was one of my biggest projects so fat, but <strong>now</strong><br>as I’ve <strong>more</strong> <strong>experience</strong> as a <strong>Frontend</strong> Engineer, I realize I <strong>didn’t</strong><br>do <strong>enough</strong> <strong>research</strong> into <strong>creating</strong> a <strong>web</strong> site with a <strong>blog</strong>.</p>
<h2>Client Side Rendering (CSR) vs Server Side Rendering (SSR) vs Static Generation (SG)</h2>
<p>When developing a <strong>web</strong> <strong>application</strong>, you should <strong>think</strong> <strong>about</strong> the type of <strong>rendering</strong> to use, while <strong>considering</strong> the <strong>requirements</strong> of the <strong>problems</strong> you want to <strong>solve</strong>.</p>
<h3>Client Side Rendering (CSR)</h3>
<p>For example, a web <strong>application</strong> like a <strong>SaaS</strong> to create tasks and manage people will have <strong>dynamic</strong> <strong>pages</strong> to show the tasks, update the cards when is edited or deleted, show notifications, etc. In this situation, a <strong>CSR</strong> would be <strong>better</strong>, to <strong>render</strong> the page <strong>each</strong> time the user <strong>request</strong> access will <strong>keep</strong> the data <strong>updated</strong>. However, a <strong>CSR</strong> needs to <strong>hydrate</strong> the page when is <strong>requested</strong>, this causes a <strong>slow</strong> <strong>first</strong> <strong>load</strong>, and uses <strong>more</strong> <strong>resources</strong> of the user’s PC.</p>
<h3>Server Side Rendering (SSR)</h3>
<p>This could be solved using <strong>SSR</strong>, this consist in <strong>generate</strong> the page in the <strong>Server</strong> where the web app is hosted <strong>using</strong> all the <strong>power</strong> that a <strong>server</strong> can provide. The problem is that a <strong>server</strong> is <strong>required</strong>, Google Cloud provides with serverless options like App Engine or Cloud Run, but you’ll need to learn about this services and how to deploy the project, so the <strong>technical</strong> <strong>knowledge</strong> is <strong>high</strong>.</p>
<p>The <strong>disadvantage</strong> of <strong>CSG</strong> and <strong>SSR</strong> is that because <strong>each</strong> <strong>page</strong> <strong>must</strong> be <strong>rendered</strong> on each <strong>request</strong>, <strong>web</strong> <strong>crawlers</strong> and <strong>search</strong> <strong>engines</strong> such as Google&#39;s will take <strong>longer</strong> to <strong>obtain</strong> <strong>information</strong> about your page, resulting in a <strong>low</strong> <strong>SEO</strong> priority.</p>
<h3>Static Generation (SG)</h3>
<p>Well, if a <strong>page</strong> <strong>doesn’t</strong> require <strong>fetch</strong> <strong>data</strong> for <strong>each</strong> <strong>request</strong>, then you could use <strong>SG</strong>, this means that the <strong>page</strong> is <strong>generated</strong> when you <strong>build</strong> the <strong>production</strong> directory <strong>before</strong> you <strong>deploy</strong> it. The page will be generated into a HTML/CSS/JS one time, and if you need to <strong>update</strong> the <strong>data</strong> in that page you’ll need to do the <strong>changes</strong> and <strong>deploy</strong> the project. Yes, you’ll need to be more cautious when reviewing the changes before deploying, but as the page is already generated, <strong>web</strong> <strong>crawlers</strong> and the Google’s <strong>search</strong> <strong>engine</strong> will get the <strong>info</strong> in your page <strong>faster</strong>, <strong>improving</strong> your <strong>SEO</strong>.</p>
<h2>The cool thing about Next.js</h2>
<p>In the <strong>past</strong> you will require to <strong>think</strong> if go <strong>full</strong> CSR, SSR or SG, linking your web to their respecting sections, like the app, blog, etc.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://nextjs.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Next.js</a></strong> is a <strong>Node.js</strong> <strong>meta-framework</strong> that uses <strong><a href="https://react.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">React.js</a></strong> to build the UI, and provides with CSR, SSR, SG and more, so you can generate SG fetching async data, allowing you to don’t <strong>need</strong> to <strong>create</strong> <strong>every</strong> <strong>static</strong> <strong>page</strong>.</p>
<p>Is that the <strong>approach</strong> <strong>used</strong> for <strong>this</strong> <strong>web</strong> site, <strong>instead</strong> of <strong>fetch</strong> the data on <strong>each</strong> <strong>request</strong>, I only <strong>fetch</strong> data <strong>when</strong> I <strong>create</strong> the <strong>build</strong> of the project.</p>
<p><strong>Each</strong> <strong>article</strong> is a SG page, but I use a <strong>template</strong> to keep every blog similar, using <strong>markdown</strong> syntax for the content of the blog, and with an <strong>extension</strong> of <strong>TailwindCSS</strong> I keep the styles consistent.</p>
<p>So, <strong>Next.js</strong> allows you to <strong>choose</strong> the <strong>rendering</strong> method for <strong>each</strong> <strong>page</strong> in your web, this feature permits to create amazing websites in the same project, keeping consistence and with fast load times, Next.js even lazy loads each page and start loading when you hover a link like Home, Contact, etc.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I’ll explain in more detail the architecture of this project in the future!</p>
</blockquote>
<h2>TailwindCSS vs MUI</h2>
<p>I choose to use <strong><a href="https://tailwindcss.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">TailwindCSS</a></strong> to learn about this CSS library, and I’m impressed the <strong>faster</strong> that makes the development of the styles of a web project. <strong>MUI</strong> <strong>provides</strong> <strong>functionalities</strong>, but sometimes <strong>gives</strong> <strong>problems</strong> with <strong>hydration</strong> like in my previous website, when you <strong>first</strong> <strong>load</strong> the page it takes a <strong>time</strong> to <strong>show</strong> all the <strong>styles</strong>, now it no longer occurs because TailwindCSS is pure CSS and the pages are static.</p>
<h2>Deploying on Vercel</h2>
<p><strong><a href="https://vercel.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vercel</a></strong> is the company behind Next.js, and they provides with <strong>hosting</strong> services <strong>optimized</strong> for <strong>Node.js</strong> apps, and as I’m learning about Cloud Development maybe I could try to host this web like my previous web into a Cloud Service like Cloud Run, but this time I choose to use <strong>Vercel</strong> to get the <strong>analytics</strong> that are very useful, and as the <strong>hobby plan</strong> gives me free hosting for small projects.</p>
<p>To deploy I use the <strong><a href="https://vercel.com/docs/cli" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vercel CLI</a></strong>, pretty simple and straightforward.</p>
<h2>More content coming soon!</h2>
<p>I’ll keep updating with posts, features and more content to share my experience, and know I’m writing this paragraph, I think the next feature it would be a newsletter to notify people when I create a new post. Time to work!</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://juancman.dev/en/blog/website-2.0</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://juancman.dev/en/blog/website-2.0</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[Tech]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Human to JS]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>Human to JS</h1>
<p><img src="/projects/human-to-js-banner.png" alt="Human to JS banner"><br><em>Human to JS diagram</em></p>
<p><PostData
  date='14 de Abril del 2023'
  author='Juan Manzanero'
  website='https://human-to-js.juancman.dev'
  github='https://github.com/juancmandev/human-to-js'
/></p>
<h2>Retrospectiva</h2>
<p>Siempre estoy buscando crecer mi carrera aprendiendo nuevas tecnologías como buen Ingeniero en Software; sin embargo, eso puede ser peligroso ya que la Ingeniería en Software no es sobre usar el último tech stack, sino de hacer que las cosas ocurran.</p>
<h2>Fuente de inspiración</h2>
<p>Estaba revisando Twitter hasta que encontré un tweet de una persona que había creado un <strong>side project</strong> en un fin de semana. Ese proyecto es <a href="https://www.sqltranslate.app/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SQL Translator</a>, una simple UI para escribir un texto describiendo una consulta, entonces obtienes la consulta en código SQL, ¡simple!</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/whoiskatrin?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw%7Ctwcamp%5Etweetembed%7Ctwterm%5E1634973237829599233%7Ctwgr%5Eb49b9d28e6ea7383ef16ea3c8c6040656ff0c944%7Ctwcon%5Es1_&ref_url=https%3A%2F%2Fpublish.twitter.com%2F%3Fquery%3Dhttps3A2F2Ftwitter.com2Fwhoiskatrin2Fstatus2F1634973237829599233widget%3DTweet" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@woiskatring</a> usó la API de ChatGPT para enviar un prompt escrito por el user, devolviendo una respuesta en SQL dentro de un component para copiar al portapapeles. Eso fue suficiente para obtener la atención merecida por la comunidad. <a href="https://twitter.com/whoiskatrin/status/1634973237829599233" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tweet link</a>)</p>
<h2>Mi idea</h2>
<blockquote>
<p><em>¿Por qué no una web app para escribir un prompt y genera código JavaScript?</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Así que comencé a construir mi idea usando este tech stack:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Next.js</strong>: Framework web para construir la UI y como Next.js provee un directorio API para comunicarte con la API de ChatGPT</li>
<li><strong>MUI</strong>: Para usar los UI components como sistema de diseño</li>
<li><strong>Fromik &amp; Yup</strong>: Para manejar el estado del formulario del prompt y crear esquemas de validación</li>
<li><strong>react-syntax-highlighter</strong>: Para mostrar la respuesta de ChatGPT</li>
</ul>
<p>Usando todas estas tecnologías construí una UI simple usando el MUI Card component, entonces creé el form donde manejé todos los inputs con Formik, los inputs de tipo text y select son los por defecto de MUI, y para crear el esquema de validación usé Yup para marcar como required aquellos inputs para no enviarlos vacíos.</p>
<p>Con la UI finalizada, comencé a crear el endpoint en el directorio de la API para consumir la API de ChatGPT, tan solo usando un fetch como en el proyecto de <a href="https://twitter.com/whoiskatrin?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw%7Ctwcamp%5Etweetembed%7Ctwterm%5E1634973237829599233%7Ctwgr%5Eb49b9d28e6ea7383ef16ea3c8c6040656ff0c944%7Ctwcon%5Es1_&ref_url=https%3A%2F%2Fpublish.twitter.com%2F%3Fquery%3Dhttps3A2F2Ftwitter.com2Fwhoiskatrin2Fstatus2F1634973237829599233widget%3DTweet" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@whoiskatrin</a>. indicando qué modelo de OpenAI utilizar, en este caso <em>text-davinci-003</em>, puedes aprender más de los esos modelos <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/api-reference/models/list" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">aquí</a>. Obviamente en la petición envié el prompt del user dentro de un string indicando a ChatGPT que solo me de el código, sin comentarios o resultados adicionales.</p>
<h2>Valor añadido</h2>
<p>Sí, hay opciones como GitHub Copilot que resuelven ese problema, y eso es por qué agregué la opción de escoger qué tipo de sintaxis usar, arrow function o simple function.</p>
<p>Añadiré más features, como una opción para TypeScript, y usar una TS Interface para que se use como referencia, ¡pero ahora estoy trabajando en más proyectos!</p>
<h2>Inspirando personas</h2>
<p>Lo genial de los side projects is que inspira personas como nosotros, podemos usar nuestras habilidades técnicas que llevan el pan a la mesa para transformar ideas en productos, y productos en comunidades, tal como <a href="https://twitter.com/serudda" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@Serudda</a> habla en este <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LXgPNdw8avI&t" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">video</a>.</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://juancman.dev/en/projects/human-to-js</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://juancman.dev/en/projects/human-to-js</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[ChatGPT]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Next.js]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[JavaScript]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Vercel]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Workarise]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h1>Workarise</h1>
<p><img src="/projects/workarise-banner.png" alt="Workarise Banner"><br><em>Workarise Banner</em></p>
<p><PostData
  date='13 de Abril del 2023'
  author='Juan Manzanero'
  website='https://human-to-js.juancman.dev'
  github='https://github.com/juancmandev/human-to-js'
/></p>
<h2>Descripción General</h2>
<p><a href="https://workarise.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Workarise</a> es un Software como Servicio para administrar equipos mediante task cards asignadas a personas, establece una fecha de inicio y final, agregar archivos, etc.</p>
<p>Puedes usar el Calendario para ver las fechas de entrega de las tareas y agendar eventos de Google Meet autorizando el uso de tu Google Calendar. Puedes editar y borrar eventos los cuales se sincronizan con tu Google Calendar y el de los invitados. El Gantt te provee con una línea del tiempo para ver la duración de las tareas.</p>
<p>La web app está desarrollada con <a href="https://react.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">React.js</a>, usando <a href="https://vitejs.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vite.js</a> para correr el entorno de desarrollo. Para funcionalidades como modals y popovers usamos <a href="https://mui.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MUI</a>. Para manejar el estado de los componentes usamos useContext.</p>
<p>Para crear eventos Google Meet y sincronizar el calendario hemos desarrollado una pequeña API con Node.js para usar la API de Google OAuth 2, ya que necesitamos pedir permiso para acceder al Google Calendar del user.</p>
<p>Actualmente, Workarise está en su primera versión, usando <a href="https://firebase.google.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Firebase</a> para autenticar a los users, guardar datos y archivos. Firebase utiliza <a href="https://firebase.google.com/docs/firestore" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Firestore</a>, una Base de Datos NoSQL, sin embargo estamos desarrollando una API con <a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Django</a> corriendo en <a href="https://cloud.google.com/run" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cloud Run</a>) conectado a <a href="https://cloud.google.com/sql" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cloud SQL</a> a una instancia MySQL, ya que usaremos una Base de Datos SQL en el futuro. Actualmente la web app y la landing están desplegadas en Firebase Hosting, pero moveremos la landing a Vercel, y será actualizada a Next.js in el futuro para optimizar el SEO y publicar blog posts.</p>
<h2>Mi impacto en Workarise</h2>
<p>Actualmente, estamos desarrollando un MVP, y todos estamos a tiempo parcial en este proyecto. Me uní en Diciembre, pero antes no había un producto que los users pudieran usar, y como era el único Ingeniero Frontend en ese momento tomé toda la responsabilidad de entregar algo que pudiera considerarse un MVP.</p>
<p>Me tomó alrededor de 3 meses para conseguir eso, actualicé algunas de las dependencias del proyecto para mejorar el flujo de desarrollo, y sugerí usar Firebase como Backend y Hosting.</p>
<p>Gracias a todo esto obtuvimos nuestros primeros users y feedback, así que ahora estamos trabajando con ese feedback para mantener mejorando nuestra app, ¡a nuestros users les gusta el diseño y la simplicidad!</p>
<p>Ahora mismo hay 3 engineers en el equipo, 2 en el front (incluyéndome) y 1 en el back, pero estoy ayudando a nuestra Backend Engineer para desplegar en GCP a producción la API y Base de Datos, y estoy guiando al nuevo Frontend Engineer para entregar nuevos features, él ha desarrollado el responsive design y algunos features que complementan las task cards.</p>
<p>Estoy feliz de poner a prueba mis habilidades en este proyecto, no es fácil tomar más responsabilidad con menos de 2 años de experiencia laboral, y me ha ayudado a crecer mucho en estos meses.</p>
<p>Incluso si el mercado no considera mis años como senior, creo que eso no importa tanto, lo único que importa es que puedas entender por qué usas código, para crear soluciones y alcanzar a las personas a través de sus computadoras.</p>
]]></description>
            <link>https://juancman.dev/en/projects/workarise</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://juancman.dev/en/projects/workarise</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[React.js]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Vite.js]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[MUI]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Firebase]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[GCP]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[Node.js]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Juan Manzanero]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>